Barry Moser Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Barry Moser Papers.
1968-1998.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Moser, Barry.
34 linear feet.
Barry Moser had already established a reputation for himself as the premier American engraver of woodcuts in the 20th century before he turned to working primarily on designing and illustrating children's books. Moser has worked on over 200 books. He is the winner of an American Book Award. Barry Moser takes an active role in the design of any book that he illustrates, often contributing to type choice, layout, and cover design.
MSS19920050
Biography
Barry Moser was born in Tennessee in 1940. He attended college at Auburn University, the University of Tennessee at Chattanooga, and did graduate work at the University of Massachusetts at Amherst. Educated as a painter, Moser took an interest in wood engraving and his first engravings appeared in 1968. He also took an interest in book design, and had illustrated and designed over 100 books before turning to watercolors and children's literature in 1987. Moser won the American Book Award in 1983 for his engravings and design for Alice in Wonderland. Editions published under Moser's private imprint, the Pennyroyal Press, are prized by collectors.
Since 1987, Moser has illustrated and designed a wide range of children's books, totalling close to 200 books for his career. Moser has worked with a wide variety of publishers and authors, but as a book designer he takes a leading role in selecting the type and layout for his books, in addition to providing the illustrations. Moser has also written several books on his own and has also adapted a number of classic children's stories. He has even co-written a series of books with his youngest granddaughter about the family pets.
Moser now lives near Northampton, Massachusetts, and works at home. He enjoys spending time with his dogs and his grandchildren when not at work, but he continues to follow an aggressive schedule. He is currently completing the design of an edition of the Bible that will feature 400 original illustrations.
Scope and Content
The holdings do not include many original watercolors, but it does contain a wide assortment of supplementary materials used in the design and production of Moser's children's books. An effort has been made to group materials by project title - most items relating to a specific book have been boxed together. Correspondence is retained with with the book title to which it relates. Some of Moser's records, including book contracts and color art transparencies, are stored in a separate box.
The collection consists of material which arrived at the Dodd Research Center in at least three different, but unidentified, accessions. All organic materials have been photocopied and removed from the collection.
Arrangement
Collection consists of a single series arranged by project.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to children's literature and associated artwork. See especially, Gerald Hausman, author of the Turtle Island Alphabet (illustrated by Moser), is also represented at the Dodd Center.
The Dodd Center also holds some of Moser's Pennyroyal Press editions, including his design for Frankenstein. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Bibliography
Information gathered from collection materials, including biographical copy from a number of book jackets. Some additional resource material was obtained via the World Wide Web - links to Moser-related material can be found by an author search at www.yahoo.com.
About the Author:
McDuffie, Dena.“Barry Moser: A Dreamer of Dreams,” Firsts The Book Collector's Magazine,v. 9, no. 11 November 1999 .pp. 28-45. (Dodd Periodicals)
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Illustrated books, Children's.; Children's literature—Connecticut illustrators.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Personal Papers.; Manuscripts.; Production Proofs.; Galleys.; Photographs.
Occupations:
Artist.; Engraver.; Book designer.; Author.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated by the artist in installments.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Projects, 1968-1998
  - The Adventures of Sherlock Holmes
    - Photos, color jacket proof with set of color art proofs, 1 pc. color art copy, 1 pc. unfinished watercolor art (older A.C. Doyle), concept art copies, design notes, contract copy, correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 27:, Folder 1)
    - Complete dummy with paste-in text and paste-in illustration copies, ca. 1991 (Box 27:, Folder 2)
  - The Ali Jahdu Storybook
    - Lettering studies, copies of art proofs (some with corrections), various color art proofs, ca.1991 (Box 17:, Folder 1)
    - Dummy with paste-in text and paste-in art copies (with corrections), ca.1991 (Box 17:, Folder 2)
    - 2 pcs. watercolor art (not used), layout and design sheets, ca.1991 (Box 17:, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, design notes, front end proofs and copy text, 1990-1991 (Box 17:, Folder 4)
    - 2 MS copies, 2 sets type proofs (one set labeled “moser/master”, other set is later with notes/corrections), 1990-1991 (Box 17:, Folder 5)
    - Photocopy of galley (with text and art, with some corrections), ca.1991 (Box 17:, Folder 6)
  - And Still the Turtle Watched
    - Concept photos, 1989 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - Typescipt dummy, art concept dummy (with pencil sketches), dummy with color art copies attached, 1989 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - 3 pencil sketches, concept art with some pencil additions, concept clippings and copies, 1989 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, color art proofs, color art copies, calligraphy, 1989 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
    - Color galleys, photocopy mechanicals preliminary jacket comp., 1989 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Appalachia: The Voices of Sleeping Birds
    - Color transparencies, concept photos by Moser, ca.1991 (Box 6:, Folder 1)
    - Contract, correspondence, MS typescript, sample proof copies, set of folded and gathered color proofs, packet of prelim. jacket design copies, 1990-1991 (Box 6:, Folder 2)
    - Copies of concept photos, lettering and calligraphy studies, 1 pc. watercolor lettering (“A”), layout notes, clipping, 1990-1991 (Box 6:, Folder 3)
    - Layout design sheets, early page proof photocopy with correction marks, 2 sets of color galleys, jacket proofs, alternate cover design composites (set of three), 1991 (Box 6:, Folder 4)
  - Ariadne, Awake!
    - Photo, 1 pc. pencil sketch (unused art), copies of concept art, copies of prelim. line art, ca.1993 (Box 18:, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, color thumbnail page for cover designs, design notes, lettering studies, early (partial) MS copy, 1993-1994 (Box 18:, Folder 2)
    - Type proof (with corrections), MS typescript, 1993 (Box 18:, Folder 3)
    - Color jacket proof (with corrections), partial set of color proofs (art and chapter headings), layout and design sheets, 1993-1994 (Box 18:, Folder 4)
  - Around the World in Eighty Days
    - Correspondence, 1 pc. color art proof, 4 pcs. lettering transparencies (for cover paste-up), ca. 1989 (Box 15:, Folder 1)
  - Atrium Gallery Poster
    - 2 (2 sided) posters w/ artwork by Moser, 1994 (Box 25:, Folder 1)
  - The Ballad of Biddy Early
    - Correspondence, concept art copies, lettering studies, jacket proof, 1989 (Box 10:, Folder 1)
    - 1 pc. color art for title lettering, partial sheet from color galley proof, layout design sheets, copies from dummy (with paste-in art copies?), ca. 1989 (Box 10:, Folder 2)
  - Beauty and the Beast
    - Clippings relating to Wilderstein house, 1989-1991 (Box 2:, Folder 1)
    - Concept photos, 1991-1992 (Box 2:, Folder 2)
    - Concept clippings, copies, 1991 (Box 2:, Folder 3)
    - Print copies of engravings (for shooting?), correspondence, title page layout designs, and a few engraving prints by other artists (materials tests?), 1991-1992 (Box 2:, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, proof pages, and 2 MS versions, 1991-1992 (Box 2:, Folder 5)
    - Revised type proof, with correspondence, 1991 (Box 2:, Folder 6)
    - 4 jacket proofs (with different lettering colors), galley photocopy, some proof sheets, layout design sheets, 3 sheet ovelay for p.25, and 1 paste-up emblem design, 1991-1992 (Box 2:, Folder 7)
  - Bingleman's Midway
    - Correspondence, 3 MS copies (one w/ hand-lettered corrections), design notes, 1 pc. “preview” design page with rough pencil sketch thumbnails, 1994-1995 (Box 10:, Folder 1)
    - Miniature dummy with paste-in text and concept art copies, set of folded and gathered leaves with jacket proof, 2 photocopies of miniature dummy (w/ variant corrections), 2 sets of type proofs (one w/ corrections), set of copies of title page lettering, 1994-1995 (Box 10:, Folder 2)
    - 2 pcs. prelim. pencil sketches, concept art copies, concept art collages, layout and design sheets, 1994-1995 (Box 10:, Folder 3)
  - A Brilliant Streak: The Making of Mark Twain
    - Correspondence, lettering studies, copies of sample proof pages, 1996-1997 (Box 23:, Folder 1)
    - Copy of MS typescript (w/ corrections), copy of MS (w/ copied corrections), copies of concept photos, ca. 1995-1996 (Box 23:, Folder 2)
    - Type proofs, galley proof (type only), layout and design notes, color copy of jacket design art, ca. 1995-1997 (Box 23:, Folder 3)
  - The Call of the Wild
    - Correspondence, photocopy concept photos, proof “dummy” with corrections (dated 8/94), 5 pcs. b/w art proofs, paste up of revised colophon, 1992-1994 (Box 3:, Folder 1)
    - Early text proof (no illustrations) (pages pasted onto scrap paper), 1994 (Box 3:, Folder 2)
    - Floppy disk (3.5 inch, text in Quark format with fonts and graphics), dummy set with printed text and copied illustrations pasted in, 1994 (Box 3:, Folder 3)
    - Copy of galley proofs with pasted illustrations and corrections, 1994 (Box 3:, Folder 4)
    - Calligraphy and lettering samples, layout design sheets, 1994 (Box 3:, Folder 5)
  - Charles A. Lindberg: A Human Hero
    - Correspondence, jacket proof, layout and design notes, copy of MS typescript, 1996-1997 (Box 21:, Folder 1)
  - Cloud Eyes
    - Correspondence, 2 MS versions, 2 sets of type proofs photocopy concept photos, design notes, copies of finished art, 1994 (Box 3:, Folder 1)
    - Set of unbound folded leaves with hardcover, galley test pages, set of galley proofs, jacket proof, dummy with pasted copies of prelim. art, lettering and layout design pages, 1994 (Box 3:, Folder 2)
    - Layout design sheets, copy of galley set with corrections, oversize copy of galley set, galley sheets (“2nd proof”), copies or art proofs (marked “ok”), 1994 (Box 3:, Folder 3)
  - Dippers
    - MS typescript with text notes for illustrations, type samples in various fonts, correspondence, typescript telescript of program “The Home for Blind Women” (by same author as Dippers), copy text and illustrations for “scientific” description of Dippers, 3 pcs. prelim. pencil sketches on transparency stock, 3 pcs. color copies of finished art, 1997 (Box 8:, Folder 1)
    - 1 pc. sample paper stock, copy of galley proof (text only, ill. pages blank), dummy with some text and handwritten notes for illustrations, 5 pcs. design/ composition for jacket design, ca. 1997 (Box 8:, Folder 2)
    - Copy of galley set with illustrations, ca. 1997 (Box 8:, Folder 3)
  - The Dreamer
    - Correspondence, copy text for jacket, MS copy, concept copies, lettering and layout designs, rough dummy with pencil thumbnails, set of folded galleys, 1993 (Box 5:, Folder 1)
    - Jacket proof, color art proofs (no text), layout and design notes, galley copy with Moser's corrections, partial galley copy with corrections, jacket copies, 1993 (Box 5:, Folder 2)
  - East of the Sun and West of the Moon
    - Correspondence, calligraphy and lettering design for title (includes paste-up), layout and design notes, photocopies of art plates, galley sheet (p. 19), partial proofs with corrections, 1988-1989 (Box 5:, Folder 1)
    - Concept art photos w/ negatives, clippings, photocopies of concept photos, clippings, 1988 (Box 5:, Folder 2)
    - MS copy with copied corrections, MS copy with corrections, MS copy with notes by Moser, 1988-1989 (Box 5:, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, set of art galleys, copy of art galleys with comments, copy of full galley with corrections, copy of jacket design, 1988-1989 (Box 5:, Folder 4)
  - Ever Heard of an Aardwolf?
    - Correspondence, design notes, partial typescript (laser print?), 13 pcs. engraving test prints, ca. 1995 (Box 21:, Folder 1)
  - Face to Face
    - Copies of select page proofs, copies of lettering studies, prelim. designs for lettering, correspondence, ca. 1990 (Box 25:, Folder 1)
    - Layout design sheets, ca. 1990 (Box 25:, Folder 2)
  - The Farm Summer 1942
    - Correspondence, MS copy, illustration notes (by author?), various type samples, 1992-1993 (Box 9:, Folder 1)
    - 3 pcs. prelim. pencil sketches, “thumbnail” illustration planning sheet, jacket design paste-up (color art copy with lettering on transparency overlay), concept art copies (w/ 9pcs. on transparency stock), 1992-1993 (Box 9:, Folder 2)
    - Concept art copies, clippings, ca. 1992 (Box 9:, Folder 3)
    - Layout and design sheets (1 pc. w/ large pencil sketch and design notes), prelim. jacket proof, title page mock-up, variant title, color galley set, jacket proof, color copy galley set (not final version?), concept art copies, concept art collages, 1992-1993 (Box 9:, Folder 4)
  - Fly! A Brief History of Aviation
    - Correspondence, photos, design notes, copies of concept photos/clippings, 1992-1993 (Box 9:, Folder 1)
    - 2 MS copies (dot printing), MS copy (laser printing), partial copy of MS proof (with corrections), font size sample pages, “timeline” MS copy, 1992-1993 (Box 9:, Folder 2)
    - MS copy (dot printing, heavy corrections, dated 7/29/92), 4 MS copies (laser printing, various dates, with corrections), 1992-1993 (Box 9:, Folder 3)
    - Partial dummy for “historical notes” section (paste-in text and photocopied photos), set of folded and gathered galley leaves (stapled, no cover), jacket proof, uncut color galley sheet (2nd half of book), 1992-1993 (Box 9:, Folder 4)
    - Complete dummy with paste-in text and paste-in illustrations (marked with corrections), ca. 1993 (Box 9:, Folder 5)
    - 3 sets type proofs (“galley 1”, copy of “galley 1”, and “galley 2”), 16 pcs. color art galleys (loose), 17 pcs. color copies of art proofs, 1992-1993 (Box 9:, Folder 6)
    - Layout and design sheets, publication “Museum of Flight News” for Sept. 1992 (concept art?), 3 uncut proof sheets (art only, no text), 5 pcs. full-size copies from dummies/paste-ups (part of layout and design material), 1992-1993 (Box 9:, Folder 7)
  - Fifty Days of Solitude
    - MS copy with copied corrections and some photograph copies, ca. 1993 (Box 6:, Folder 1)
      (part of MS)
    - Correspondence, copy of partial type proof, layout and design sheets for jacket, text, 1993-1994 (Box 6:, Folder 2)
  - A Game of Catch
    - Correspondence, folded and gathered leaves with jacket, set of “production first proofs”, 1 pencil sketch, lettering samples, design notes, 2 text copies (from previous publications), concept art clipping, 1993-1994 (Box 6:, Folder 1)
    - Selected proof copies with copied corrections, set of “production first proofs” (galleys), 3 pcs. oversized (2 pg. spreads), 1993-1994 (Box 6:, Folder 2)
  - Ghost Horse of the Mounties
    - Publication of previous paperback edition, 1983 (Box 15:, Folder 1)
    - Partial copy of rough dummy (shows thumbnail art design, layout), full dummy with paste-in text and paste-in thumbnail illustrations, ca. 1988 (Box 15:, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, various calligraphy and lettering studies for title, 1987-1989 (Box 15:, Folder 3)
    - Book jackets, copies of cover illustration, copies of concept photos, copies from dummy, 1988-1989 (Box 15:, Folder 4)
  - Good and Perfect Gifts
    - Dummy w/ paste-in text and art copies (some corrections), ca. 1996 (Box 24:, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, design notes, MS copy labeled “final manuscript - 11.09.94”, photos, concept art copy, 1994-1996 (Box 24:, Folder 2)
    - Jacket design mock-up, color copies of variant jacket designs, 1 pc. color art (design ornament), ca. 1996 (Box 24:, Folder 3)
    - Layout and design notes, 3 sets of color galley proofs with jacket proofs (2 sets w/ endpaper proofs), 2 pcs. `sample repro. pages', photos, group of color copies on various papers of nativity engraving (engraving used in text), 1994-1997 (Box 24:, Folder 4)
  - Grass Songs
    - Correspondence, copies of concept photos, 2 MS type copies, 1988-1992 (Box 13:, Folder 1)
    - Dummy w/ paste-in text, dummy with text and paste-in copies of illustrations (includes notes/corrections), ca. 1992 (Box 13:, Folder 2)
    - “Production first proof” folded and gathered leaves with jacket (on white paper), set of folded and gathered leaves with jacket, jacket proof, 1 pc. art proof, 1993 (Box 13:, Folder 3)
    - Set of “specimen first proof” galleys (single pages cut, not folded) with jacket proof, set of “specimen second proof” with jacket proof, 1993 (Box 13:, Folder 4)
    - 2 sets marked “specimen second proof” with jacket proofs, 1993 (Box 13:, Folder 5)
  - I am the Dog, I am the Cat
    - Correspondence, MS copy, design notes, 1993-1994 (Box 6:, Folder 1)
    - 23 pcs. prelim. pencil sketches, concept art copies (two copies on transparency stock), 1993-1994 (Box 6:, Folder 2)
    - Layout and design sheets, 1 pc. watercolor art (not used in final?), type proof with corrections, lettering studies, concept art copies, 1993-1994 (Box 6:, Folder 3)
  - I Had Seen Castles
    - Correspondence, concept art copies, MS type copy, jacket proofs, folder cover w/ design notes, 1993 (Box 14:, Folder 1)
  - I See the Moon
    - Layout design sheets, ca. 1994 (Box 25:, Folder 1)
  - International Literacy Year Poster
    - Correspondence, lettering studies (includes watercolor studies), lettering proofs, concept art copies, 1987-1990 (Box 22:, Folder 1)
  - The Iron Woman
    - MS copy (to compositor), type proof copy, 1994 (Box 4:, Folder 1)
    - MS copy (with illustrations - by Moser?), copies from The Iron Giant (also by Ted Hughes), 1968, 1994 (Box 4:, Folder 2)
    - 5 partial pencil sketches, clippings, concept art copies, cover layout designs, 1994 (Box 4:, Folder 3)
    - Dummy with pasted proof text and pasted art proofs, 1994 (Box 4:, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, layout and design notes, partial type proofs, contract copy, 1994 (Box 4:, Folder 5)
    - Layout design sheets, 1994 (Box 4:, Folder 6)
  - Journey
    - Correspondence, lettering samples, concept art copies, photocopy of galley proof, copies of font samples, layout sheet, cover design, b/w print of cover art, 1 pc. original art for cover design, 1990-1991 (Box 20:, Folder 1)
  - Jump!
    - Layout, production notes, 1986 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - Typesetting, proof sheets, 1986 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - Photocopy mechanicals, additional production materials, proof of white back cover for paperback edition, and original pencil sketch of Br'er Rabbit provided by Moser to NCLC in 1992., 1986 - 96 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Jump Again!
    - Correspondence, design notes, type proofs w/ corrections, 3 versions MS typescript w/ corrections, copy of Susan Sontag story from The New Yorker (relevance?), copies of funny “alternative” art for Br'er Rabbit jumping, 1986-1987 (Box 23:, Folder 1)
    - Uncut galley proof sheet w/ art and text (very large sheet - kept folded)., 1987 (Box 23:, Folder 2)
    - Various proof copies, set of copies of galley proofs (w/ slight corrections), 1987 (Box 23:, Folder 3)
  - Jump on Over!
    - Dummy w/ paste-inn text and paste-in ill. copies, ca. 1989 (Box 21:, Folder 1)
    - Copies of MS typescript (2 sets, different versions), set of type proofs, 1989 (Box 21:, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 5 pcs. prelim. art pencil sketches, copies of concept art, clippings, lettering samples, photo, 3 pcs. type proofs (front end material), 1989 (Box 21:, Folder 3)
  - Just So Stories
    - Correspondence, design notes, lettering studies, various line art/lettering designs on transparency paper, set of color art proofs, 1995-1996 (Box 21:, Folder 1)
  - Kashtanka
    - Correspondence, manuscript, and design materials, 1991 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - Pencil sketch, transparency, jacket comp., cover, proof, two unbound galley copies, 1991 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - Galley sets, layout and design sheets, 1991 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - The Life of George Washington
    - Correspondence, copies of concept art, lettering designs, photocopy of MS typescript, 1990-1991 (Box 21:, Folder 1)
  - Life Work
    - Correspondence (1 pc.), jacket proofs, 1993 (Box 22:, Folder 1)
    - Copy of galley proof (w/ slight corrections), 1993 (Box 22:, Folder 2)
  - Little Tricker
    - 13 pcs. original pencil sketches, lettering studies, dummy photocopy (paste-in text and illustrations), ca. 1990 (Box 25:, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, MS copy with corrections, lettering studies, copy of article on Ken Kesey, 1989-1990 (Box 25:, Folder 2)
    - Photos, clippings, concept art copies, prelim. art copies, issue of Vis a Vis magazine(March 1989) with article on Ken Kesey, 1989-1990 (Box 25:, Folder 3)
    - Layout design sheets (1 pc. w/ paste-in color proof), ca. 1989 (Box 25:, Folder 4)
  - The Magic Hare
    - Correspondence, contract copy, color copy of jacket art, b/w copies of jacket art, layout design color prints (one w/ corrections), photocopy MS as sent to typesetter, 1991-1992 (Box 14:, Folder 1)
    - 2 MS typed photocopies (2nd copy has two additional stories), ca. 1991 (Box 14:, Folder 2)
    - 2 type proof copies (one with corrections), 1992 (Box 14:, Folder 3)
  - The Magic Wood
    - 2 sets folded and gathered leaves with jackets, correspondence, color copies of art (reduced size), MS copies, “rough” dummy with pencil sketches and type paste-in, contract, 1991-1992 (Box 5:, Folder 1)
    - 16 pcs. production transparencies, 1991-1992 (Box 5:, Folder 2)
    - 2 pcs. uncut galley sheets, 2 sets of galleys (labeled “second proof” and “first proof with Barry's comments”), type proof sheets, 1 pc. hand-lettering for title, jacket art proof, 1991-1992 (Box 5:, Folder 3)
  - The Many Lives of Ben Franklin
    - Correspondence, jacket proof, lettering studies, concept art copies, clippings, layout notes, photocopy of MS typescript, 1989-1990 (Box 22:, Folder 1)
  - Messiah
    - Correspondence, research and design notes, MS copies, type proofs with corrections, 1989-1991 (Box 4:, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, MS copies, intro MS, jacket proofs and jacket copy MS, early text proof with corrections, 1989-1991 (Box 4:, Folder 2)
    - 13 pcs. colr art proofs (“Second proof”), 3 pcs. “Christ symbol” ornament design + 4 copies of ornament, white cardboard sheet with rectangular cutout, 3 pcs. lettering samples, 3 pcs. original art watercolors (errors or unused pieces), dummy with text only + corrections, partial dummy with type-proof intro and afterword, 1990-1991 (Box 4:, Folder 3)
    - 2 sets folded and stapled leaves, 3 jacket proofs (alt. versions), 1992 (Box 4:, Folder 4)
    - Numerous color copies of art from the book (with alternate crucifixion scene? + unused portrait of Handel?), 1991-92? (Box 4:, Folder 5)
    - Approx. 10 different sets of type proofs (most with corrections), set of uncut galleys, layout design sheets, 8 pcs. original calligraphy/ornament designs, poster layout design with related color copy, 1991-92 (Box 4:, Folder 6)
  - Mother Goose Collection